Whatever it is. Good morning.
Today is August 31st, it's the 9th of אלול. Elul. My name
is Dan Margulis, I'm filling in. Rabbi Linzer has יארצייט yahrtzeit for
his mother this morning. And we are going to be picking up
on מ"ה עמוד ב' mem hey amud bet around 10 of the
last 10 narrow lines where it says אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. So
this is discussing the laws of סקילה skila that we were picking
up from yesterday. אמר שמואל נקטעה יד העדים פטור. Amar Shmuel niktata
yad ha'edim patur. If the hands of the witnesses after the
גמר דין, gmar din, the witnesses' hands are cut off, Micha, we
just started so you didn't miss anything.
נקטעה יד העדים פטור. Niktata yad ha'edim patur. Then the person who's
going to be executed will be off the hook. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? דבעינא יד העדים תהיה בו בראשונה וליכא. D'ba'ina yad ha'edim tihyeh
bo barishona v'leika. Because the פסוק pasuk requires that the witnesses be
the ones to execute the person first. But the hand, so if
their hand was cut off, יד העדים תהיה בו בראשונה, yad ha'edim
tihyeh bo barishona, so there's a requirement that they be the first
hand to throw the stone. And it's impossible if they have no
hand. Therefore, the person would be off the hook for this execution.
Now, to have all these formal requirements, so maybe it's both hands,
either way, whatever it is, the point is that in such a
circumstance, the claim of שמואל Shmuel is that the person would be
off the hook for this execution.
He says נקטעה יד העדים, niktata yad ha'edim, both? Has to be
both because at least one of the witnesses would have to do
it, but I'm not sure of the detail of that. Okay, אלא
מעתה, ela me'ata, would you really take this to the farthest extreme,
עדים גידמים דמעיקרא? edim gidimim d'me'ikara?
That if the witnesses have are have amputated hands even from before
the the crime was committed,
הכי נמי דמפסלי? hacha nami d'mifsli? So no, because
in this case it was that they they had hands and the
hand was severed afterward, it creates a פסול, psul, it creates a
disqualification after the fact. שאני התם דאמר קרא יד העדים Shani hatam
d'amar kra yad ha'edim because the פסוק pasuk says יד העדים yad
ha'edim the hand of the witnesses שהייתה כבר, she'hayta kvar, it's like
the hand was already in existence. But in a case where they
had they were amputees from before the time of the crime, then
it wouldn't be a disqualification. It's only a disqualification if they had
hands at the time of the crime and the hand was severed
afterward. That is a hand that existed at the time of the
crime has to be the hand to cast the first stone. Okay.
מיתבי Meitvei is going to be challenged. כל מקום שיעידו שנים ויאמרו
מעידים אנו באיש פלוני שנגמר דינו בבית דין פלוני ופלוני ופלוני עדיו
הרי זה יהרג. Kol makom she'yidu shenayim v'amru me'idim anu b'ish ploni
shenigmar dino b'beit din ploni u-ploni v'ploni edav harei zeh yehareg. So
what if two people come to court and say, we are testifying
that this person actually had a גמר דין gmar din in another
בית דין beit din with these two other people as witnesses? We
were just watching the court case, but we saw who were the
witnesses and what was the crime and who this person was. But
for whatever reason the person wasn't executed in that court.
He ran away maybe.
He ran away maybe, or there was some disqualification perhaps. What if
those two witnesses who convicted him, their hand their hands were chopped
off for something like that? So הרי זה יהרג, harei zeh yehareg,
so he should be put to death at this בית דין. beit
din. So תרגמה שמואל, targama Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel has to defend himself,
בהן הן עדיו. b'hen hen edav. No, it must be that actually
the same witnesses came. It's not it couldn't be a case where
two other people testify about seeing a court case, that wouldn't be
enough to create the requirement to execute a person. What's interesting about
that is the הוה אמינא havamina at least or the suggestion from
that ברייתא braita is that you don't actually need witnesses of the
crime to execute the person. Even witnesses of a בית דין beit
din case that convicted the person is enough now to execute the
person. That's very interesting, because those witnesses never actually saw the crime
take place. And that's part of why שמואל Shmuel seems to be
rejecting it. Fundamentally the witnesses who execute the person have to be
the witnesses who saw him commit the crime.
So the בית דין beit din themselves go, let's say he ran
away. Can the בית דין beit din themselves say hey we convicted
this guy or no? You have to like go through the whole
thing again.
So even according to שמואל Shmuel it has to be the witnesses
have to come because the witnesses have to be the ones who
saw the crime. So he says הן הן עדיו, hen hen edav,
it has to be the witnesses who saw him commit the crime
have to be the ones to testify in the next court or
whatever.
They have a whole proceeding all over?
They have to have at least some amount of similar proceedings. Now
because they're testifying נגמר דינו, nigmar dino, the court case was already
resolved, I can imagine at least that it will be a quicker
process. Okay.
Yeah,
the previous statement you made, did they have to execute without the
witnesses? I didn't...
No, the הוה אמינא, havamina, the suggestion was that witnesses who observed
a case and saw that it resulted in a conviction could show
up in another court and say, oh we saw this court case
and it was a conviction, you should execute this guy. But they
never actually saw the crime. And שמואל Shmuel says no no no,
it has to be the same witnesses in both cases. That is
the same people testifying, they must have been the ones who actually
saw the crime.
What was the
question, what was the מיתבי? meitvei? So the מיתבי, meitvei, the challenge
was a case where you could have people who were disqualified witnesses
and the person won't get off the hook because two other people
will have watched the case, right? Imagine the two witnesses who saw
the crime... Their hands got chopped off and it's a freak accident.
So then we're going to say, oh, the guy gets off the
hook. But then no, two other people who watched the court case
could go to a different court and testify and have him executed,
and שמואל Shmuel says no, it would have to be still the
same witnesses and that's how שמואל Shmuel defends his position. Okay, ובעינן
קרא, u-ba'inan kra, do we really need a פסוק pasuk to teach
us that? Okay, כדכתיב, ke-dichtiv,
because based on this, דהתניא, d'hatanya, מות יומת המכה רוצח הוא. mot
yumat ha-makeh rotze'ach hu. So אין לי אלא במיתה הכתובה בו. ein
li ela be-mitah ha-ktuvah bo. So the פסוק pasuk says מות יומת
המכה רוצח הוא, mot yumat ha-makeh rotze'ach hu, the person who committed
this crime has to die because he's a murderer. So אין לי
אלא במיתה הכתובה בו. ein li ela be-mitah ha-ktuvah bo. You can
only execute someone according to the assigned punishment, the correct type of
capital punishment. So מנין שאם אי אתה יכול להמיתו במיתה הכתובה בו?
minayin she-im ee atah yachol le-hamito be-mitah ha-ktuvah bo? What if it's
impossible to give him the מיתה mitah that was assigned to him?
שאתה ממיתו בכל מיתה שאתה יכול להמיתו? she-atah memito be-chol mitah she-atah
yachol le-hamito? So how do we know that you could, if necessary,
rely on other forms of execution as a backup? תלמוד לומר מות
יומת המכה מכל מקום. talmud lomar mot yumat ha-makeh mikol makom. You
have to execute him. So the requirement to execute
overrides perhaps the obligation to specifically follow the requirements in the תורה
Torah following particular types of capital punishment for particular types of crimes.
Maybe the עדים edim have chopped off hands, you could still kill
the guy but a different way.
Right, but would kill him with a different מיתה mitah that doesn't
require the עדים edim to throw the stone, because the requirement for
the עדים edim to throw the stone only by סקילה. skilah. Okay,
שאני התם, shani hatam, so no, that's something specific, דאמר קרא מות
יומת. d'amar kra mot yumat. ונילמד מיניה משום דהוי רוצח וגואל הדם
שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. v'nilmad mineh mishum d'havei rotze'ach v'goel ha-dam shnei
ktuvim ha-ba'im k'echad. No, that's a particular לימוד limud that's learned out
regarding murderer and גואל הדם. goel ha-dam. That is, the murderer and
the גואל הדם goel ha-dam have a special requirement to permit because
in a case of murder, right, you can imagine the גואל הדם,
goel ha-dam, the whole idea that the redeemer, the relative of the
person who was killed can chase after you and get revenge, that
part of that means they could kill you however they like. It
doesn't have to be definitely with הרג hereg or anything specifically. So
those become שני כתובים הבאים כאחד. shnei ktuvim ha-ba'im k'echad. So that
דרשה, drashah, פסוק pasuk example of גואל הדם goel ha-dam are now
two examples, and the general principle we have at least according to
some תנאים tanna'im is שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. shnei ktuvim
ha-ba'im k'echad ein melamdin. If we have two examples of something, we
can't create a general principle from that to כל התורה. kol ha-Torah.
Therefore you couldn't apply the principle that if you can't rely on
this execution you'd use any means
necessary. אין מלמדין. ein melamdin. So what's the principle then? Which principle?
The principle is if we can't execute by סקילה, skilah, then we'll
do הרג. hereg. If you can't do הרג, hereg, we'll do חנק,
chenek, whatever, like whatever we need, or we'll you know give you
poison or we'll give you electric chair, some other mechanism to kill
you if the mandated mechanism won't work or or there's some disqualification.
Once we've determined that you are guilty of a capital crime, the
requirement is to execute in any means necessary. Okay, so they're trying
to say, no, but since we have two examples of that, we
can't learn that as a general principle. It only seems to apply
to רוצח rotze'ach and גואל הדם. goel ha-dam. That is, רוצח, rotze'ach,
murder and manslaughter.
But it says guy, basically, let's say the guy's being killed for
manslaughter, not for שבת. Shabbos. Right, then the עדים edim have chopped
off hands and you can't kill a different way? Right, because it's
not for שבת. Shabbos.
Right, not for שבת Shabbos or עבודה זרה avodah zarah or. Exactly,
it's limiting. It's limited to two exact cases, murder and manslaughter, yeah.
And גואל הדם goel ha-dam is the.
גואל הדם goel ha-dam is the is the family member of the
person who died by manslaughter. And the rule is that as the
person is traveling to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, the refuge city,
the גואל הדם goel ha-dam can attack that person until they reach
sanctuary. And you can't, so that's something that doesn't have to go
to court, you can just do it. Exactly, though it's going to
come up discussed extensively in מסכת מכות. Masechet Makkot. Okay.
Okay, תלמוד לומר מות יומת המכה שאתה יכול להמיתו. talmud lomar mot
yumat ha-makeh she-atah yachol le-hamito. So שאני התם דאמר קרא מות יומת
ונילמד מיניה משום דהוי רוצח וגואל הדם שני כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל
שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין
מלמדין. shani hatam d'amar kra mot yumat v'nilmad mineh mishum d'havei rotze'ach
v'goel ha-dam shnei ktuvim ha-ba'im k'echad v'chol shnei ktuvim ha-ba'im k'echad ein
melamdin. Okay, so we're
on the fourth wide line. רוצח הא דאמרן. rotze'ach ha d'amran. So
רוצח, rotze'ach, the פסוק pasuk that proves that principle by רוצח rotze'ach
is what we already saw for the פסוק pasuk from במדבר Bamidbar
about מות יומת המכה. mot yumat ha-makeh. Okay, גואל הדם מאי היא?
goel ha-dam mai hi? So what's the proof that גואל הדם goel
ha-dam has the same principle? דתניא גואל הדם ימית את הרוצח. d'tanya
goel ha-dam yamit et ha-rotze'ach. The גואל הדם goel ha-dam can kill
the manslayer. So מצוה בגואל הדם. mitzvah be-goel ha-dam. The it's a
requirement that the גואל הדם goel ha-dam do it. ומנין שאם אין
לו גואל שבית דין מעמידין לו גואל? u-minayin she-im ein lo goel
she-beit din ma'amidin lo goel? This is a fascinating principle. What if
the person who died by manslaughter has no relative or no one
wants to go and attack the the manslayer? So then the בית
דין Beit Din will appoint an official court-appointed גואל הדם. goel ha-dam.
Now what's so fascinating about this is it seems like the גואל
הדם, goel ha-dam, at least when you read the פסוקים psukim in
the תורה, Torah, is something יחם לבבו, yecham levavo, is something totally
extra-legal and spontaneous and it's not part of the legal system. It's
a special dispensation given because people have this emotional connection to their
family members. And here it's become a legislated, institutionalized part of the
the court proceedings. So it's a fascinating development in how that's presented
here, שנאמר. she-ne'emar. שנאמר shene'emar בפגעו
בו bifig'o bo when he encounters him. So any person, perhaps even
a person who's not related, who encounters the manslayer who's been authorized
by the court to do so, מכל מקום. mikol makom. So the
principle is that there is such a גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, no
matter what. That's part of how manslaughter law is dealt with in
the תורה. Torah. There has to be, you have the right to
go to the עיר מקלט, ir miklat, and the person who was
killed has the right to a גואל הדם. Goel HaDam.
Right, otherwise if there was no גואל הדם, Goel HaDam, you
never go to the עיר מקלט. ir miklat. Right. So it's sort
of perhaps just to create the motivation. Now, of course, it's a
very weighty motivation. If your life is on the line, you really
want to get there.
So this is in a sense
the גמרא's Gemara version of imprisonment rather than which?
The עיר מקלט? ir miklat?
Yeah, the fact that they're appointing somebody to induce you to go.
I'm not sure you can exactly compare it to imprisonment. You get
to live in a house, you live in this city, you got
your תורה Torah teacher gets exiled along with you. But the גמרא
Gemara is going to deal with a kind of imprisonment as well.
There are cases where even if there's
not enough witnesses or things like that, there are cases where we
put someone in an imprisonment until they starve to death. כיפה, Kippah,
yeah exactly.
Is there any control over this revenger? He might have gone.
Yeah, it's other סוגיות. sugyot. It's not for our סוגיא sugya now.
Yeah. So אמר ליה מר קשישא בריה דרב חסדא לרב אשי. amar
lei Mar Kashisha brei deRav Chisda leRav Ashi. So מר קשישא Mar
Kashisha the son of רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to רב אשי,
Rav Ashi, ומי בעינן קרא כדכתיב? u'mi ba'inan kra kideichtiv? So why
do you need that פסוק pasuk to teach that? והתנן? vehatnan? היה
אחד מהן גידם אילם חיגר סומא או חרש. haya echad mehen gidem
ilem chiger suma o cheresh. אינו נעשה בן סורר ומורה. eino na'aseh
Ben Sorer u'Moreh. What if, this is this week's פרשה, parsha, what
if either of the two parents of the בן סורר ומורה Ben
Sorer u'Moreh is either גידם, gidem, has an amputated hand, or אילם,
ilem, אילם ilem is can't speak, is mute, חיגר chiger or limps,
or סומא suma blind, חרש cheresh or is deaf, that the boy
could not be assigned to be בן סורר ומורה. Ben Sorer u'Moreh.
שנאמר shene'emar ותפסו בו, vetafsu bo, they have to grab him. ולא
גידמין, velo gidmin, that means that they have to have hands. והוציאו
אותו, vehotziu oto, ולא חיגרין. velo chigrin. And they have to take
him out, that means that they can't be limping. ואמרו, ve'amru, and
they have to say, ולא אילמין, velo ilmin, and that they can't
be mute. בננו זה, benenu zeh, they have to say 'this is
our son' and זה zeh very often means they have to be
able to designate by pointing and by vision, ולא סומין, velo sumin,
and therefore not blind. איננו שומע בקולנו, einenu shome'a bekolenu, and he
can't hear our voice. ולא חרשין. velo charshin. That is the assumption
that a חרש cheresh is אינו שומע ואינו מדבר. eino shome'a ve'eino
medaber. חרש Cheresh means also that they couldn't speak.
Meaning that if a boy was deaf, also you couldn't kill him
because אינו שומע?
eino shome'a? I will get to it when we get to פרק
בן סורר ומורה. Perek Ben Sorer u'Moreh. Okay, so but the point
is here that there are all these requirements on the parents, that
the parents of the בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u'Moreh would
that would get him off the hook for all these different reasons.
So מאי טעמא לאו משום דבעינן קרא כדכתיב? mai ta'ama lav mishum
deba'inan kra kideichtiv? So what, meaning what? Meaning, shouldn't you just say,
'Oh, but if the parents are disqualified for this reason that it
totally gets him off the hook, why not just say, Oh, but
he's still guilty so we should execute him some other way?' Okay.
לא לא שאני התם דכוליה קרא יתירה הוא. la la shani hatam
dechulei kra yetira hu. No, those are special
additional principles that are applied by בן סורר ומורה Ben Sorer u'Moreh
based on the פסוקים psukim there and nothing to do with a
more general applicability to capital crimes. תא שמע. Ta shema. אין לה
רחוב. Ein la rechov. What if a city that was going to
be עיר הנדחת Ir HaNidachat doesn't have a city square? The requirement
in the תורה Torah is you have to take all the property
from the עיר הנדחת Ir HaNidachat into the city square and burn
it there. So what if it doesn't have a city square? אינה
נעשית עיר הנדחת דברי רבי ישמעאל. eina na'aseit Ir HaNidachat divrei Rabbi
Yishmael. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael says if there's no city square, I
guess it can't be an עיר הנדחת. Ir HaNidachat. What's interesting about
this, I'm just thinking now, is some of the laws of ערובין
Eruvin also deal with, you know, questions of what's a רשות הרבים
reshut harabbim and which kinds of cities have a רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim or which don't and all sorts of things like that. Part
of the discussion some modern פוסקים poskim suggest, I think particularly ערוך
השולחן Aruch HaShulchan talks about maybe modern cities because of how our
streets are set up don't necessarily have what the גמרא Gemara considers
to be רשות הרבים reshut harabbim that has to be sort of
the single primary main street of the town. Most cities don't have
that. We have many different streets. So here רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says if there's no רחוב, rechov, there's no main city square, then
it can't be עיר הנדחת. Ir HaNidachat. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva
omer, אין לה רחוב, ein la rechov, עושין לה רחוב. osin la
rechov.
Then you just make a city square in order to be able
to fulfill the מצוה. mitzvah. By, first you clear out some of
the houses I guess to make a square, and then you put
the property there and burn it. So עד כאן לא פליגי אלא
דמר סבר רחוב דמעיקרא בעינן. ad kan lo pligi ela demar savar
rechov deme'ikara ba'inan. The only disagreement between רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael is that רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael thinks the
city square has to have been there from before it was designated
עיר הנדחת. Ir HaNidachat. ומר סבר רחוב דהשתא נמי כדמעיקרא דמי. u'mar
savar rechov dehashta nami kidmei'ikara dami. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva thinks
that even a city square which is only made after the fact
counts as good enough. It counts as if it was there from
before. אבל דכולי עלמא בעינן קרא כדכתיב. aval dechulei alma ba'inan kra
kideichtiv.
But everyone agrees, both of them agree that you need a city
square like is what required in the
תורה, Torah, that is.
So what are we trying to prove from this?
We're trying to prove that there are necessary conditions on capital crimes
or certain מצוות mitzvot in תורה Torah that if they're not fulfilled
we can't follow through with the punishment. We can't if your parent
if the parents of the בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u'moreh are
blind or one of them we can't execute him and we don't
have a backup plan to execute him some other way. So these
are all proofs against the idea that remember שמואל'ס Shmuel's suggestion was
that עדים edim could get off if the עדים edim had their
hands cut off the מחלל שבת mechallel Shabbat would get off the
hook because he couldn't be executed. And then the challenge to שמואל
Shmuel was well maybe there's just a backup principle. Backup principle was
if we can't execute you this way we should execute you in
any way possible. So here these are proofs in a number of
different contexts interesting עיר הנידחת Ir HaNidachat is talking about burning the
property rather than well it's also talking about beheading all of the
people in the city but that's not that doesn't require a רחוב
rechov right? The רחוב rechov is for the property but that's a
requirement of עיר הנידחת Ir HaNidachat in general. So the point is
that these are all necessary conditions on application of the הלכה. halacha.
That is if there's no רחוב rechov you just can't do it.
There's no no way to follow through.
שמואל'ס Shmuel's the one that says that the עדים edim don't have,
right, that supports שמואל Shmuel that is there was a challenge to
שמואל Shmuel and this is now all defense of שמואל. Shmuel. Okay,
so תנאי היא. tanai hi. So this really goes back to a
מחלוקת תנאים machlokes tanaim דתנן: ditnan: אין לו בוהן יד בוהן רגל
אוזן ימנית. ein lo bohen yad bohen regel ozen yemanit. What if
a מצורע metzora the purification process of a מצורע metzora involves the
right thumb, the right big toe, and the right ear ridge being
covered with blood and with olive oil throughout the purification process. So
what if the מצורע metzora has no right thumb or has no
right toe or has no right ear? What are you supposed to
do? אין לו טהרה עולמית. ein lo taharah olamit. He could never
become טהור tahor because the purification process is limited by that necessary
condition of application of blood and oil to those body parts. רבי
אליעזר אומר נותן על מקומו ויוצא. Rabbi Eliezer omer noten al mekomo
veyotze. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you could just put it on
the place where the thumb or the big toe or the ear
was. It's just it's not a necessary condition. It's it's the first
attempt and if he doesn't have then you do something similar. Okay.
רבי שמעון אומר נותן על שמאלו ויוצא. Rabbi Shimon omer noten al
smolo veyotze. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon gives a different so it's an
interesting debate between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
Both of them think there's a second a backup plan. רבי שמעון'ס
Rabbi Shimon's backup plan is left instead of right. רבי אליעזר'ס Rabbi
Eliezer's backup plan is in the same place even without the limb.
So the מחלוקת machlokes between רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon might be sort of what is going on with this
טהרה taharah process. Are we talking about it has something to do
with the thumb and the toe and the ear or is it
that it has to do something with the right side and the
left side? Something obviously for a further discussion. One point to note,
this is something very much in common between the purification of the
מצורע metzora and the inauguration of the כהנים, Kohanim, the מילואים, miluim,
is that they have this application of blood and oil onto the
thumb, toe, and ear.
There's a lot of commonalities between going from a regular ישראל Yisrael
to being a כהן Kohen and going from a מצורע metzora to
being regular ישראל. Yisrael. So those kind of jumps in קדושה kedushah
are parallel. Okay, we're up to the next משנה. mishna. כל הנסקלין
נתלין דברי רבי אליעזר. kol haniskalin nitlin divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says everyone who is executed by stoning also has to
be hanged. Now hanging is described here as we're already a bit
familiar with is not hanging execution by hanging but is a display
of the body after the person has been executed. That is putting
them up on a pole or on some kind of frame, a
gallows, but not execution by hanging. וחכמים אומרים אינו נתלה אלא המגדף
ועובד עבודה זרה. vachachamim omrim eino nitlah ela hamigadef ve'oved avodah zarah.
The חכמים Chachamim say the only two עבירות aveiros that you get
תליה telyiah for hanging are מגדף migadef blasphemy and עובד עבודה זרה
oved avodah zarah if you worshipped idolatry. האיש תולין אותו פניו כלפי
העם. ha'ish tolin oto panav klapei ha'am. A man is hanged with
his face facing outward. והאשה פניה כלפי העץ. veha'ishah paneha klapei ha'etz.
And a woman is hanged with her face facing toward the beam,
the wooden beam. דברי רבי אליעזר. divrei Rabbi Eliezer. That's רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer's position. וחכמים אומרים האיש נתלה ואין האשה נתלית. vachachamim omrim
ha'ish nitleh ve'ein ha'ishah nitlet. The majority opinion. A man would be
hanged and a woman is never even hanged at all.
So אמר להם רבי אליעזר. amar lahem Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer said back to the חכמים. Chachamim. והלא שמעון בן שטח תלה
נשים באשקלון? vehalo Shimon ben Shetach talah nashim be'Ashkelon? So
and he says back but didn't שמעון בן שטח Shimon ben Shetach
that is many generations earlier in the period of the זוגות, Zugot,
didn't he hang many women in אשקלון? Ashkelon? It's also interesting אשקלון
Ashkelon is not in ירושלים Yerushalayim so it gets into interesting questions
of the where did they have a סנהדרין Sanhedrin that was able
to put people to death even in other cities? Okay, so he
hanged these women in אשקלון. Ashkelon. אמרו לו שמונים נשים תלה amru
lo shemonim nashim talah and they said about him that he hanged
eighty women ואין דנים. ve'ein danim. In אשקלון. Ashkelon. It's also interesting,
אשקלון Ashkelon is not in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so it gets into interesting
questions of the where did they have a סנהדרין Sanhedrin that was
able to put people to death even in other cities. Okay, so
he hanged these women in אשקלון. Ashkelon. אמרו לו, Amru lo, שמונים
נשים תלה, shmonim nashim tala, and they said about him that he
hanged eighty women. ואין דנים שנים ביום אחד. Ve'ein danim shnayim beyom
echad.
So that was in one day, but you can't judge two cases,
two in one day. So we're going to have a discussion, the
גמרא, Gemara, what does that exactly mean? The גמרא Gemara says, תנו
רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. So this is a ברייתא braita version. והומת ותלית,
Vehumat vetalita, they said: you execute him and you hang him. יכול
כל המומתין נתלין, Yachol kol hamumatin nitlin, maybe you should say every
single type of execution requires hanging? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, כי קללת
אלהים תלוי, ki kilelat elohim taluy, because a פסוק pasuk says: it
is a curse for God a body left hanging. That is, the
requirement is to bury the body relatively soon after the hanging takes
place. To fulfill the מצווה, mitzvah, what they would do is they
would have the execution, they would basically put the body up right
before sunset so that they would, the person would be up maybe
a few seconds and they would take them down. That's the requirement
described in the גמרא, Gemara,
because it is an affront to God to leave the body overnight.
We're going to see because the decay of the body, even for
a criminal, is repulsive. So מה מקלל זה שבסקילה, ma mekallel zeh
shebiskilah, so a מקלל, mekallel,
someone who cursed God, that is a מגדף, megadef, is executed by
סקילה, skilah, is executed by stoning. אף כל שבסקילה דברי רבי אליעזר.
Af kol shebiskilah divrei Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learns from
a דרשה drasha from the word קללת kilelat that it means reference
to the מגדף megadef and therefore everyone who is executed by סקילה
skilah should have תלייה tliyah as well. והחכמים אומרים מה מקלל זה
שכפר בעיקר, Vehachamim omrim ma mekallel zeh shekafar be'ikar, a person who
blasphemed God has denied the belief in the monotheistic true belief in
God. אף כל שכפר בעיקר, Af kol shekafar be'ikar, so anyone who
denies the source of the universe, that is also someone who worships
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. It's interesting the connection between מגדף megadef and
עובד עבודה זרה. oved avodah zarah. The רמב״ם Rambam in הלכות עבודה
זרה Hilchot Avodah Zarah פרק ב Perek Bet says: why did I
include מגדף megadef in the laws of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? You
could imagine other sections of הלכה halachah he could have put מגדף.
megadef. He says it's because of this גמרא Gemara that connects מגדף
megadef and עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. That is someone who denies or
questions God's authority and really expressed that in a very extreme way.
כפר בעיקר Kafar be'ikar has denied God and so too worshipping עבודה
זרה avodah zarah is denial of God. Okay, במאי קמיפלגי? Bemai kamipalgi?
So what do they disagree about? רבנן דרשי כללי ופרטי. Rabbanan darshi
klalei ufratei. So the חכמים's Chachamim principle is that we learn by
כלל ופרט. klal ufrat. כלל ופרט, Klal ufrat, a general followed by
an exclusion. Okay. ורבי אליעזר דריש ריבויי ומיעוטי. VeRabbi Eliezer darish ribuyei
umiutei. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learns inclusion and exclusion. So what's
the difference between כלל ופרט klal ufrat and ריבוי ומיעוט? ribui umiut?
If you look in רש״י, Rashi, this last רש״י Rashi on the
page. רש״י Rashi says, יש חילוק בין זה לזה. Yesh chiluk bein
zeh lezeh. There's a difference between the two. פרט היינו פירוש הכלל.
Prat hainu peirush haklal. The פרט, prat, that is when we have
כלל ופרט, klal ufrat, the פרט prat is explaining what the כלל
klal is. ואין בכלל אלא מה שבפרט. Ve'ein baklal ela mah shebaprat.
It limits the entire application of the כלל klal to what's in
the פרט, prat, the specific case. ואפילו הוא דומה לפרט אין מתרבה
מן הכלל. Ve'afilu hu domeh laprat ein mitrabeh min haklal. Even something
that's similar to the פרט prat we couldn't include because the פרט
prat is very limiting. It's a very precise kind of דרשה. drasha.
אבל הדורשו במיעוט לא עקר את הכלל ממקומו אלא מיעוטו מקצת מתחילה
היה משמע כל דבר ובא המיעוט ומיעט משמעו. Aval hadorsho bemiut lo
akar et haklal mimkomo ela miuto miktzat mitchilah hayah mashma kol davar
uva hamiut umiet mashmao.
So ריבוי ומיעוט ribui umiut is just it sounds very general, מיעוט
miut means it limits it but it's not כלל ופרט, klal ufrat,
פרט prat to a very precise case, it's just מיעוט, miut, it
limits it to a more narrow range of applications. And that's the
difference between חכמים Chachamim and רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer learns it by מיעוט. miut. He takes the general principle execution
and limits it to only סקילה. skilah. And the חכמים Chachamim take
a general principle execution and limit it specifically to a case of
מגדף megadef and עבודה זרה avodah zarah which is somewhat similar to
מגדף. megadef. So only those two cases. Okay. רבנן דרשי כללי ופרטי.
Rabbanan darshi klalei ufratei.
So what's the כלל ופרט klal ufrat that the rabbis learn? והומת
ותלית, Vehumat vetalita, you execute him and you hang the body. כלל.
Klal. כי קללת, Ki kilelat, פרט. prat. So it's a general principle
followed by an exclusion, only קללת אלהים תלוי, kilelat elohim taluy, a
curse of God. אי הוו מקרבי להדדי אמרינן אין בכלל אלא מה
שבפרט. Ei havuy mekarvei lehadadi amrinan ein baklal ela mah shebaprat. If
they would have been next to each other we would learn that
only what was in mentioned in the פרט prat will apply the
כלל. klal. הני אין מידי אחרינא לא, Hani in midi achrina lo,
so only to case like this and not to any other case.
השתא דמרחקי מהדדי, Hashta demarchakei mehadadi,
but since they are farther apart from each other, that is that
textually, exactly, that the פסוק pasuk has some words in between. Okay.
Because it says ותלית אותו על עץ, vetalita oto al etz, לא
תלין נבלתו על העץ, lo talin nivalto al ha'etz, right. So they're,
it's not in the same פסוק pasuk even. Okay. So because they're
separated, השתא דמרחקי מהדדי אתא הני לריבויי. hashta demarchakei mehadadi ata hani
leribuyei. So maybe
that's why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it seems to include one more
thing according to the רבנן. Rabbanan. עבודת כוכבים דדמי ליה בכל מילי,
Avodat kochavim dedami leih bechol milei, because עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim is
similar to מגדף. megadef. ורבי אליעזר דריש ריבויי ומיעוטי. VeRabbi Eliezer darish
ribuyei umiutei. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer learns by expansion and limitation.
והומת ותלית, Vehumat vetalita, so והומת ותלית vehumat vetalita you execute him
and you hang him. And you hang the body is a ריבוי,
ribui, is a general principle. כי קללת Ki kilelat מיעוטא miute and
then it limits it. אי הוי מקרבי הדדי I havye mikarvei hadadei
if they had been closer together, לא הוי מרבינן אלא עבודה כוכבים
lo havye marbinan ela Avoda Kochavim I would have only applied it
to עבודה כוכבים Avoda Kochavim דדמי de-dami that's similar to מגדף, megadef,
so דדמי ליה בכל מילי de-dami le be-chol milei
that's similar in every way. השתא דמרחקי מהדדי Hashta de-merchaki me-hadadei but
since they're far apart from each other, אתי לריבויי atei le-ribuiyei שאר
הנסקלים shear ha-niskalim so Rabbi Eliezer thinks we should expand it to
include everyone who's executed by סקילה. skila. That is, we have either
the principle it's כלל ופרט klal u-prat but since they're far apart
we should expand it a little bit more. It's more expansive than
a regular כלל ופרט, klal u-prat, and according to Rabbi Eliezer, it's
מיעוט ריבוי ומיעוט miut ribui u-miut which is very expansive, but since
they're a little bit closer together, we'll limit it. If they had
been farther apart, we would have made it even more expansive. So
they're having a little bit of a disagreement but they agree about
most of the core דרשה, drasha, but because they're using a slightly
different technique, they have this מחלוקת. machloket. Okay.
In general, ריבוי ומיעוט ribui u-miut is going to include more, will
be more inclusive.
Exactly, that's Rashi's point because the idea is the מיעוט miut just
comes to limit the ריבוי, ribui, it doesn't totally exclude the כלל
klal by the פרט. prat. פרט Prat is a specific case, so
כלל ופרט klal u-prat is very limiting.
Okay. So we're on מ"ו ע"א Mem Vav Amud Aleph the next
piece. האיש תולין. Ha-ish tolin. So מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? So why
this is the opinion of חכמים Chachamim is that we only that
the man is facing outward and the woman is facing backward, maybe
the woman is not hanged at all according to Rabbi Eliezer, so
those
מחלוקות. machlokot. האיש תולין Ha-ish tolin וכולי. ve-chulei. מאי טעמא דרבנן? Mai
ta'ama de-rabbanan? So why do the Rabbis say אמר קרא ותלית אותו?
amar kra ve-talita oto? אותו ולא אותה. Oto velo otah. You only
hang him but not her, because the פסוק pasuk says אותו, oto,
him. לרבי אליעזר, Le-Rabbi Eliezer, אותו ולא כסותו. oto velo ksuto. We
learn that you hang him, that is a person, any person you
hang them naked but not wearing clothing. That's at least in part
because when they're executed by סקילה skila already we remove the clothing
as we learned yesterday in order to facilitate a faster death. You
might have thought that that means the הוה אמינא hava amina is
that maybe you would put clothing on them before they're hanged onto
the dead body so that they'd be more show more respect to
the person.
But at least in part the whole purpose of this display of
the body after execution is to shame the person for their crime.
So that's part of what's going on here as well, so בלא
כסותו belo ksuto you hang them naked. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, אי הכי נמי,
i hachi nami, of course you hang them naked because you already
learned that by סקילה. skila. Okay. אלא אמר קרא וכי יהיה באיש
חטא, Ela amar kra ve-chi yihye be-ish chet, so it's regarding a
person who has a sin, איש ולא אשה. ish velo isha. So
they learn by a different דרשה. drasha. It's that it refers to
a man but not a woman. לרבי אליעזר, Le-Rabbi Eliezer, האי וכי
יהיה באיש hai ve-chi yihye be-ish מאי דריש ביה? mai darish bei?
So what does Rabbi Eliezer do with that פסוק, pasuk, a פסוק
pasuk that says it applies to a man but not a woman?
So אמר ריש לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, ההוא למעוטי בן סורר ומורה.
hahu le-miutei ben sorer u-moreh. That comes to exclude בן סורר ומורה.
ben sorer u-moreh. We do not, according to Rabbi Eliezer who says
we hang everyone who's executed by סקילה, skila, nonetheless there's one exception
which is בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u-moreh. Why? Because בן סורר
ומורה ben sorer u-moreh is still a boy, he's not a man
yet, he's not called איש. ish. Okay. והתניא, Ve-hatanya, and we have
a ברייתא, braita, בן סורר ומורה נסקל ונתלה דברי רבי אליעזר. ben
sorer u-moreh niskal ve-nitla divrei Rabbi Eliezer. Ah, but isn't there a
version of Rabbi Eliezer's opinion in this ברייתא braita that says that
even a בן סורר ומורה ben sorer u-moreh when he's stoned to
death then we would hang the body? אלא אמר רב נחמן בר
יצחק, Ela amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, so Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
interprets it differently, לרבות בן סורר ומורה. le-rabot ben sorer u-moreh. It
comes to include בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u-moreh. Even though he's
not a man yet, nonetheless we would hang the body according to
Rabbi Eliezer. So מאי טעמא דאמר קרא וכי יהיה באיש חטא? mai
ta'ama de-amar kra ve-chi yihye be-ish chet? איש ולא בן. Ish velo
ben. חטא. Chet. So a man's sin but not a boy's sin.
So מי שעל חטא נהרג, mi she-al chet neherag, so someone who's
killed for his sin. But יצא בן סורר ומורה שעל שום סופו
נהרג. yatza ben sorer u-moreh she-al shum sofo neherag. Ben sorer u-moreh
is not actually killed for what he did. What did he do?
He ate some meat, he drank some wine, he didn't listen to
his parents. Not such a terrible thing. But he's killed נידון על
שם סופו nidon al shem sofo as the גמרא Gemara is going
to deal with extensively in פרק בן סורר ומורה. Perek Ben Sorer
u-Moreh. It's a preemptive kind of execution. And therefore
he's excluded from the principle of איש כי יהיה בחטא מות ish
ki yihye be-chet mavet because he doesn't have a sin per se
that was for what he was executed for, he's being executed preemptively.
So הוי מיעוט אחר מיעוט, havei miut achar miut, and that's a
double exclusion. ומיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות, ve-miut achar miut ela lerabot,
and we have when we have two exclusions one after another, there
it comes to include. Different explanations of how that works exactly, why
that is, either because it's redundant or because the second one comes
to limit the first limitation which means an expansion because it's a
double negative, something like that.
אמר, Amar, yeah, he's being executed preemptively. You know, isn't there a
law like that somebody's not executed, you know, if somebody's going to
do something in the future they can't be executed now for those
sins, right? In the תורה Torah they talk about...
Well, except בן סורר ומורה, ben sorer u-moreh, right? בן סורר ומורה
Ben sorer u-moreh is the classic example. The גמרא Gemara says it's
נידון על שם סופו. nidon al shem sofo. He's executed preemptively on
the fear of what kind of a person he'll grow up to
be.
Obviously the classic case is ישמעאל, Yishmael, right? ישמעאל, Yishmael, God saves
ישמעאל Yishmael because He says באשר הוא שם. ba-asher hu sham. באשר
הוא שם, Ba'asher Hu Sham, he judged him according to exactly how
he was at that moment and not assessing what he would turn
out to be later. So there's a lot more to be said
about that; certainly, we could deal with it more when we get
to פרק בן סורר ומורה. Perek Ben Sorer Umoreh. Okay. אמר להו
רבי אליעזר והלא שמעון בן שטח תלה נשים וכולי. Amar Lehu Rabbi
Eliezer Vahalo Shimon Ben Shetach Tala Nashim Vechulu. So what about the
case of שמעון בן שטח? Shimon Ben Shetach? אמר רב חסדא לא
שנו אלא בשתי מיתות. Amar Rav Chisda Lo Shanu Ela Bishtei Mitot.
So this is the principle, right, the last line in the משנה:
Mishnah: אין דנין שנים ביום אחד. Ein Danin Shnayim Beyom Echad. You
can't judge two cases in one day. So what does רב חסדא
Rav Chisda say that means? בשתי מיתות, Bishtei Mitot, that is two
different types of execution. You can't have a case of סקילה skilah
and a case of הרג hereg on the same day. Rather, אבל
במיתה אחת דנין. Aval Bemita Achat Danin. You could do two סקילה
skilah cases on the same day. And since all of the
witches' cases that שמעון בן שטח, Shimon Ben Shetach, right, or we're
not there yet, right? He just says נשים nashim in the משנה.
Mishnah. Okay, במיתה אחת דנין. bemita achat danin. והא מעשה דשמעון בן
שטח דמיתה אחת הוי. Veha Maaseh DeShimon Ben Shetach Demita Achat Havai.
So in the case of שמעון בן שטח Shimon Ben Shetach must
have been a case where they were all being executed for the
same type of execution. ואמרו ליה דאין דנין? Veamru Leh Deein Danin?
And that's
so the disagreement is whether they were all of one type of
מיתה mita and they would agree with that or that שמעון בן
שטח's Shimon Ben Shetach case was actually multiple different types of execution
where they would have been problematic. אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר. Ela
I Itmar Hachi Itmar. This is how you should teach the משנה.
Mishnah. לא שנו אלא במיתה אחת כעין שתי מיתות. Lo Shanu Ela
Bemita Achat Keein Shtei Mitot. It's one execution that's like two executions.
היכי דמי? Heichi Dami? What are we talking about? כגון שתי עבירות.
Kegon Shtei Averot. Like two different types of sin that even if
they carry the same punishment.
אבל במיתה אחת ועבירה אחת דנין. Aval Bemita Achat Vaavera Achat Danin.
Then we would deal with that case. That is two basically identical
cases on the same day. Two cases of עבודה זרה, avodah zarah,
two cases of חילול שבת, chillul Shabbos, two cases of something like
that. Okay. מתיב רב אדא בר אהבה. Mativ Rav Ada Bar Ahava.
רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada Bar Ahava said
challenge this.
אין דנין שנים ביום אחד אפילו בנואף ונואפת. Ein Danin Shnayim Beyom
Echad Afilu Benoef Venoefet.
Even the male and female parties in an adulterous relationship. That is
what? They have the same punishment and it's the same crime, it's
even the same
act. It's not even two separate events. It's one event. Nonetheless, רב
אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada Bar Ahava says we take that line
in the משנה Mishnah very strictly. Okay. תרגמה רב חסדא. Targema Rav
Chisda. רב חסדא Rav Chisda responded. And remember רב חסדא Rav Chisda
was the one who had a very much more expansive understanding, a
more permissive understanding of this principle. So he says what? בבת כהן
ובועלה. Bevat Kohen Uvoala. Because בבת כהן ובועלה, Bat Kohen Uvoala, a
בת כהן Bat Kohen who has an adulterous relationship is executed not
by חנק chenek like normal, but by שריפה, sreifah, one of the
few cases of שריפה. sreifah. So בבת כהן ובועלה, Bat Kohen Uvoala,
the male adulterer will be executed by חנק chenek and she'll be
executed by שריפה. sreifah. So they'll be two different מיתות mitot and
that's why even בנואף ונואפת noef venoefet is because it's two different
punishments, that must be what רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Ada Bar
Ahava was referencing and therefore it would fit within רב חסדא's Rav
Chisda opinion. או, O, or alternatively, בבת כהן וזוממי זוממיה. Bevat Kohen
Vezomemei Zomemeha. And here's an interesting principle. So בת כהן, Bat Kohen,
right, we said her punishment will be by שריפה. sreifah. If there
are עדים זוממים edim zomemim come to get her killed and are
proved false, how would we execute them? We should apply the principle
ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו. Veasitem Lo Kaasher Zamam Laasot Leachiv.
So we should give them שריפה. sreifah. Okay. But זוממי זוממיה, zomemei
zomemeha, that's a debate whether or not we would give them שריפה
sreifah or not or whether we kill them by חנק chenek because
that's the normal one. That's the סוגיא sugya at the end of
סנהדרין Sanhedrin that leads into מכות, Makkot, which is sort of why
does מכות Makkot start with עדים זוממים? edim zomemim? And then זוממי
זוממיה zomemei zomemeha everyone agrees will be executed by the normal execution,
which would be חנק. chenek. So בת כהן Bat Kohen and double
זוממים, zomemim, that is the witnesses who came to prove that she
was זוממים zomemim were proved to be זוממים. zomemim. So it's like
three sets of witnesses. In those cases, so the second set of
witnesses would be executed by חנק chenek and she would be executed
by שריפה, sreifah, because the first set of witnesses will have been
proven to be telling the truth and the second set of witnesses
were proven to be lying by the third set of witnesses. Okay.
תניא רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר. Tanyu Rabbi Elazar Ben Yaakov Omer.
רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב Rabbi Elazar Ben Yaakov says שמעתי שבית דין מכין ועונשין שלא
מן התורה. Shamati Shebeit Din Makin Veonshin Shelo Min HaTorah. This general
principle, according to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi Elazar Ben Yaakov, there
are times, there are specific instances where the בית דין beit din
can go, have extra-legal enforcement abilities. And this is as I was
telling David earlier a few last week, this is something that's dealt
with extensively by the רן Ran in one of his דרשות. drashot.
The principle that the בית דין beit din has a certain amount
of elastic power. And also worth mentioning the תשובת הראש. Teshuvat HaRosh.
I think I forget which סימן siman it is, but the הראש
Rosh has an extensive תשובה teshuvah where there was a case of
someone who was an informant on the Jewish community to the Spanish
government at that time, to the king. And the community so the
הראש Rosh wanted to execute this person because the הראש Rosh was
coming from Germany and the הראש's Rosh principle at least he felt
that the modern-day rabbinic authorities still retain a certain amount of elastic
authority. And in Spain they didn't practice that way and the הראש
Rosh was upset that they wouldn't be able to execute him. So
he said what they should do is they should cut out his
tongue, which is not anything ever mentioned in the תורה. Torah. So
therefore... Extra legal and other sorts of enforcements that are perhaps so
discussed extensively. Okay, so רבי אלעזר בן יעקב שמעתי שבית דין מכין
ועונשין שלא מן התורה ולא לעבור על דברי תורה. Rabbi Elazar ben
Yaakov shamati shebeit din makin veonshin shelo min haTorah velo la'avor al
divrei Torah. It's not that they're going against the principles of the
תורה. Torah. It's not that they're doing something which isn't allowed. אלא
כדי לעשות סייג לתורה. ela kedei la'asot syag laTorah. The whole point
is to protect the תורה's Torah's laws. So someone's violating the תורה's
Torah's laws and there's no way to enforce it or there's someone
who's gone above and beyond what's normally to be allowed, nonetheless we
have to have a certain amount of protection for that. ומעשה באחד
שרכב על סוס בשבת בימי יוונים והביאוהו לבית דין וסקלוהו. umaseh be-echad
sherachav al sus be-Shabbat bimei Yevanim ve-hevi'u-hu le-Beit Din ve-sekalu-hu. There was
a case of someone riding on a horse on שבת Shabbat in
the Hellenistic period, the Hasmonean period, and they brought him to בית
דין Beit Din and they stoned him to death. Now, wait a
second, riding on a horse on שבת Shabbat is what kind of
prohibition?
דאורייתא? De-Oraita? דרבנן? De-Rabbanan? דרבנן. De-Rabbanan.
It's שבות. Shvut. We said it's a גזירה gezirah שמא shema that
you're going to take a branch from the tree to whip the
horse. So they executed him. So what do you mean? You can't
execute people for איסורי דרבנן. issurei De-Rabbanan. That was what was necessary
in that place. So what does the גמרא Gemara say? לא מפני
שראוי לכך אלא שהשעה צריכה לכך. lo mipnei she-ra'uy lekach ela she-ha-sha'ah
tzericha lekach. It's not because it was a suitable punishment for
that, but it was that generation, that time period, there was so
much חילול שבת, Chilul Shabbat, there was so much disregard, perhaps even
we could say people took the דאורייתא De-Oraita laws of שבת Shabbat
very seriously but people were very lax with their observance of דרבנן,
De-Rabbanan, and so the rabbis said we have to enforce the דרבנן
De-Rabbanan even as severely as the דאורייתא De-Oraita to impress upon people.
You could imagine perhaps the דרבנן De-Rabbanan had only recently been legislated,
so if it was a recent development, people maybe weren't keeping it
yet and they had to rule very strictly in order to enforce
it. Yeah.
It should be a principle that, you know, you should know the
consequences of your action before you commit the crime.
Well obviously that's why we have התראה. hatra'ah. So obviously there must
not have been a case of התראה hatra'ah here either because they
would have said, oh you're violating a rabbinic rule about שבת Shabbat
and he would have said, oh, you know, whatever, and you say
oh we're going to whip you in court and he'll say fine
whatever I don't care, and they bring him to court and they
kill him. So that's an interesting question. Okay. מעשה באדם אחד שהטיח
עם אשתו תחת התאנה. ma'aseh be-adam echad she-hitiach im ishto tachat ha-te'enah.
There was a certain man who was sexually involved with his wife
in public underneath the fig tree. והביאוהו לבית דין והלקוהו. ve-hevi'u-hu le-Beit
Din ve-hilku-hu. And they whipped him. Now there's no prohibition on having
sex in public. There's no such הלכה. halacha. It's just not appropriate.
So the בית דין Beit Din at that time, the גמרא Gemara
says, לא מפני שראוי לכך אלא שהשעה צריכה לכך. lo mipnei she-ra'uy
lekach ela she-ha-sha'ah tzericha lekach. It's not that that was the appropriate
punishment, technically there is no punishment for doing that, but because it
was inappropriate and it was deemed beyond what was to be tolerated
in society, the rabbis at that time decided he deserved to be
punished for that. Okay, so the משנה Mishnah continues, we have a
few more minutes, we can at least read some of the משנה
Mishnah going on to the next page. Obviously it's a long chunk
of משנה, Mishnah, we could maybe get up to the גמרא Gemara
and leave that for שבת. Shabbat. So כיצד תולין אותו? keitzad tolin
oto? How do they hang him? משקעין את הקורה בארץ. meshaki'in et
ha-korah ba-aretz. They plant the board, a wooden beam, into the ground.
והעץ יוצא. ve-ha-etz yotzei. And then there's a horizontal board that comes
off of the vertical board. Okay, ומקיף שתי ידיו זו על גב
זו ותולה אותו. u-makif shtei yadav zo al gav zo ve-toleh oto.
They tie the hands together and they hang him that way. רבי
יוסי אומר הקורה מוטה על הכותל. Rabbi Yosei omer ha-korah mutal al
ha-kotel. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei says no, they don't put it into
the ground, they just lean a beam against the wall ותולה אותו
כדרך שהטבחים עושים ve-toleh oto ke-derech she-ha-tabachim osim and they hang him
up the way butchers hang up
an animal that's being flayed. ומתירין אותו מיד. u-matirin oto mi-yad. And
then they untie him immediately. That is as soon as they tie
the person up, they untie them again
immediately. Okay, ואם לן, ve-im lan, if he left him overnight, עובר
עליו בלא תעשה over alav be-lo ta'aseh then that's a violation of
a negative מצווה mitzvah in the תורה Torah שנאמר לא תלין נבלתו
על העץ כי קבור תקברנו כי קללת אלוהים תלוי. shenemar lo talin
nivlato al ha-etz ki kavor tikberenu ki killat Elohim talui. The פסוק
pasuk says you cannot leave the body hanging overnight, and there's a
positive מצווה mitzvah and imperative to bury the body immediately כי קללת
אלוהים תלוי. ki killat Elohim talui. It's a curse against God to
leave the body hanging. כלומר מפני מה זה תלוי? klomar mipnei mah
zeh talui? Why is this one being hung? מפני שבירך את השם
mipnei she-beirach et HaShem because he cursed God ונמצא שם שמים מתחלל
ve-nimtza Shem Shamayim mitchalel and that's a curse against God. So now
obviously I would say what's the פשט? pshat? The פשט pshat is
it's a curse against God to leave the body on display because
it's repulsive, it's disgusting. The דרש drash is also to say no,
the person who's being shamed in this way has cursed God and
if that becomes public knowledge too much—now obviously we need to have
this deterrent and we need to show upon people what happens to
people who rupture society in such a way—at the same time we
don't want to take it too far because then you're publicizing the
fact that such a shameful act took place to begin with. So
אמר רבי מאיר amar Rabbi Meir where רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
בשעה שאדם מצטער be-sha'ah she-adam mitzta'er when a person is suffering,
בשעה שאדם מצטער שכינה מה? be-sha'ah she-adam mitzta'er Shechinah mah? So what
happens to the שכינה, Shechinah, to God's presence? לשון אומרת קלני מראשי
קלני מזרועי. lashon omeret kallani me-roshi kallani me-zero'i. God as if is
saying, my head hurts and my arm hurts. That is when a
person is in pain, God also in some way expresses a similar
kind of pain. אם כן המקום מצטער על דמן. im kein ha-Makom
mitzta'er al daman. Is it really true that God suffers for the
spilled blood of wicked people שנשפך? she-nishpach? So קל וחומר kal vachomer
על דמן של צדיקים, al daman shel tzaddikim, so all the more
so when righteous people are killed that God as if suffers for
that as well. ולא זו בלבד אמרו, V'lo zu bilvad amru, that's
not the only thing they said, אלא כל המלין את מתו עובר
בלא תעשה. Ela kol hamalin et meto over b'lo ta'aseh. If they
leave the body hanging up overnight you violate
the prohibition. שחלינהו לכבודו, she-hilinhu l'chvodo, what if they left, that is
anybody, not just a body that's being hanged, but any body that's
left overnight before being buried is a violation of this לא תעשה.
lo ta'aseh.
לא תלין נבלתו על העץ, Lo talin nivlato al ha'etz, not just
על העץ, al ha'etz, but in general we don't leave the body
overnight. There are some חברא קדישאs Chevra Kadisha in fact in certain
communities that still do funerals at night. Generally in our community as
far as I know is not so common, but I've been to
some funerals like that. שחלינהו לכבודו, she-hilinhu l'chvodo, what if they left
him overnight for his own כבוד? kavod? In what example? להביא לו
ארון ותכריכין, L'havi lo aron v'tachrichin, either to bring a coffin or
to bring shrouds for him, ואינו עובר עליו. v'eino over alav. That's
not a violation because you're doing it in order to make funeral
preparations. So there's a distinction. You leave the body overnight because you
haven't made the preparations and you're just pushing it off, that's a
disrespect. But if you're doing it in order to show respect to
the body, so part of the main Halachic application of that nowadays
is what if, you know, there are many family members who want
to come in from far away, from Israel, from overseas, from California,
different things? So then we usually consider waiting to have the funeral
for another day to allow people to come in as part of
the כבוד המת, kvod hamet, that is if the family members could
be there for the funeral, that's considered שחלינהו לכבודו she-hilinhu l'chvodo as
well. Okay, yeah.
I'd just say it's just hanging by his hand, not by the
head.
Right, exactly. No, it's just, right, hanging from the hands like this.
Right. Again, we said it's not hanging execution by hanging, it's just
putting the body on display. So they would cross the hands and
tie it with a rope and connect it to the pole like
that. Okay. ולא היו קוברין אותו בקברות אבותיו, V'lo hayu kovrin oto
b'kivrot avotav, they would not bury him in the ancestral burial plot,
אלא שתי בתי קברות היו מתוקנים לבית דין. Ela shtei batei kvarot
hayu metukanim l'beit din. The court had a special criminals' graveyard where
they would bury people who had been executed in בית דין. beit
din. אחד לנהרגין ולנחנקין, Echad l'neheragin v'lenechnakin, there's one burial plot for
people who've been killed by הרג hereg and חנק, chenek, and a
separate plot for נסקלין ונשרפין niskalin v'nisrafin because of the severity of
the two different types of capital punishments, so we put the more
severe and the less severe separately. נתעכל הבשר, Nit'akel habasar, once the
flesh has decomposed, מלקטין את העצמות, melaktin et ha'atzamot, they would gather
up the bones, וקוברין אותם במקומן, v'kovrin otam bimkoman, and then they
would bury them
in that place. That is, they would not allow you to take
the bones even to the ancestral burial plot. We know that in
time of the משנה, Mishnah, most burials took place in this two-stage
process. They would inter the body usually in a cave, would wait
for the flesh to decompose, and then they would come later and
do ליקוט עצמות, likut atzamot, gathering the bones to be buried separately.
And that was the practice at that time. This is discussed extensively
in מועד קטן, Moed Katan, and is not usually how things are
practiced nowadays, but is an interesting shift in how burial practice has
changed. Moses Mendelssohn and רבי יעקב עמדין Rabbi Yaakov Emden got into
a controversy in what, 18th century, about there was the whole concern
about vampires and werewolves and things at that time. And there was
a question, can we leave the body three days between the time
of burial and then
from the time of death until burial? And different, Moses Mendelssohn tried
to defend that practice that was imposed by the government, and רבי
יעקב עמדין Rabbi Yaakov Emden opposed it.
There might be alive.
Right, there was a concern people would still be alive and different
things. So anyway. Oh by the way, yeah,
the bones were replaced in the, it's not in the text, but
this is what they're suggesting. It does, the bones after would go
into the family's ancestral plot.
Well, במקומן, bimkoman, so it's a debate what במקומן bimkoman means. במקומן
bimkoman means in the place where they are, or במקומן bimkoman means
whether they would bring to their ancestral plot. That's part of the,
right, so that's a debated issue. Okay. Is there archaeological evidence
that they used to bury like this or of the בית דין
beit din plot?
All over Israel.
It's supposedly in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, I would think, I don't know if
we
have, I don't know what would
distinguish this from any other burial plot.
You should be able to identify burned bodies.
No, but remember the burning is not burning, but the burning isn't
burning the bones, right? They pour molten lead down your throat, so
it doesn't affect the bones.
נתעכל הבשר מלקטין
את העצמות.
Nit'akel habasar
melaktin
et ha'atzamot.
So after a year, when the muscles have decayed and it's just
the bones left, then you would ליקוט עצמות. likut atzamot.
So that's נתעכל הבשר.
nit'akel habasar. That what? Oh, the lead? Oh, well,
anyways, we also don't know at what point did they shift how
שרפה sreifah was practiced. Anyway, we don't know exactly. You know, the
משנה Mishnah is written, this is part of the critical sort of
modern question which is how, it's not just a modern question, it's
a later question as well, the laws in the משנה, Mishnah, many
of them... could have been instituted by the סנהדרין Sanhedrin after after
the חורבן. churban. That is, many of the ways the law of
of מיתת בית דין mitat bet din is presented may have been
instituted only after it was discontinued. So we don't actually know, we
don't have an unbiased text about what what מיתת בית דין mitat
bet din was like when it was practiced. We only have the
משנה Mishnah where further legislation could have taken place after the practice
was discontinued. So who knows. Okay. I think it's 8:30 so we
really should stop now. I'm sorry we didn't get onto עמוד ב,
amud bet, I'll leave it for Rabbi Linder to finish up tomorrow
on שבת. Shabbat. I hope everyone has—oh wait tomorrow is Friday. Wow.
Oh, see my brain is totally okay. Have a good one for
the day everybody. Thank you.